What is it that French people do better than all the others?
ما هو الشيء الذي يجيده الفرنسييون دون غيرهم؟
If you would take polls,
إذا ما أجريت اقتراعاً،
the top three answers might be:
قد تكون الثلاث إجابات الأولى هي:
love, wine and whining.
الحب والنبيذ والأنين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Maybe.
ربما.
But let me suggest a fourth one:
لكن دعوني أقترح الرابعة:
mathematics.
علم الرياضيات.
Did you know that Paris has more mathematicians
هل تعلمون أن باريس بها عدد من علماء الرياضيات
than any other city in the world?
أكبر من أي مدينة أخرى حول العالم؟
And more streets with mathematicians' names, too.
وعدد أكبر من الشوارع تحمل أسماء علماء رياضيين أيضاً.
And if you look at the statistics of the Fields Medal,
وإذا ما ألقيتم نظرة على إحصائيات ميدالية فيلدز،
often called the Nobel Prize for mathematics,
والتي غالباً ما تسمى بجائزة نوبل للرياضيات،
and always awarded to mathematicians below the age of 40,
ودائماً ما تعطى لعلماء الرياضيات الذين تقل أعمارهم عن 40 عاماً،
you will find that France has more Fields medalists per inhabitant
ستجد أن فرنسا تحظى بعدد أكبر من الحاصلين على ميدالية فيلدز للفرد الواحد
than any other country.
مقارنة بأي بلد آخر.
What is it that we find so sexy in math?
ما هو الشيء الذي نجده مثيراً جداً في الرياضيات؟
After all, it seems to be dull and abstract,
على الرغم من أنها تبدو مملة ومجردة،
just numbers and computations and rules to apply.
مجرد أرقام وحسابات وقواعد للتطبيق.
Mathematics may be abstract,
قد تكون الرياضيات مجردة،
but it's not dull
ولكنها ليست مملة
and it's not about computing.
وهي ليست محصورة في الحوسبة.
It is about reasoning
بل تدور حول السببية
and proving our core activity.
وإثبات جوهر نشاطنا.
It is about imagination,
هي تدور حول الخيال،
the talent which we most praise.
الموهبة التي دائماً ما نثني عليها.
It is about finding the truth.
بل تدور حول اكتشاف الحقيقة.
There's nothing like the feeling which invades you
لا شيء يضاهي الشعور الذي يجتاحك
when after months of hard thinking,
بعد قضاء شهور من التفكير المضني،
you finally understand the right reasoning to solve your problem.
حينما تفهم المنطق السليم لحل مشكلتك.
The great mathematician André Weil likened this --
شبه العالم الرياضي العظيم أندريه ويل هذا--
no kidding --
من دون مزاح--
to sexual pleasure.
بالمتعة الجنسية.
But noted that this feeling can last for hours, or even days.
لكنه لاحظ أن هذا الشعور قد يدوم لساعات أو حتى لأيام.
The reward may be big.
فقد تكون الجائزة ضخمة.
Hidden mathematical truths permeate our whole physical world.
الحقائق الرياضية الخفية تتخلل عالمنا المادي كله.
They are inaccessible to our senses
متعذر الوصول إليها عن طريق حواسنا
but can be seen through mathematical lenses.
ولكن يمكن أن ترى من خلال العدسات الرياضية.
Close your eyes for moment
أغلقوا أعينكم للحظة
and think of what is occurring right now around you.
وفكروا فيما يحدث حولكم الآن.
Invisible particles from the air around are bumping on you
جسيمات غير مرئية في الجو المحيط تصطدم بكم
by the billions and billions at each second,
بالمليارات والمليارات في كل ثانية،
all in complete chaos.
كلها في فوضى عارمة.
And still,
وإلى الآن،
their statistics can be accurately predicted by mathematical physics.
يمكن التنبؤ بإحصاءاتها بدقة عن طريق الفيزياء الرياضية.
And open your eyes now
الآن افتحوا أعينكم
to the statistics of the velocities of these particles.
لإحصائيات سرعات هذه الجسيمات.
The famous bell-shaped Gauss Curve,
منحنى غاوس الشهير الشبيه بالجرس،
or the Law of Errors --
أو قانون الأخطاء--
of deviations with respect to the mean behavior.
للانحرافات فيما يتعلق بالسلوك المتوسط.
This curve tells about the statistics of velocities of particles
هذه المنحنى يخبر عن إحصائيات سرعات الجسيمات
in the same way as a demographic curve
بنفس طريقة المنحنى الديموغرافي
would tell about the statistics of ages of individuals.
في الإخبار عن إحصائيات أعمار الأفراد.
It's one of the most important curves ever.
إنه أحد أهم المنحنيات على الإطلاق.
It keeps on occurring again and again,
حيث يستمر في الحدوث مراراً وتكراراً،
from many theories and many experiments,
من خلال عدة نظريات وتجارب،
as a great example of the universality
كمثال رائع للعالمية
which is so dear to us mathematicians.
وهي الشيء العزيز علينا كرياضيين.
Of this curve,
في ما يتعلق بهذا المنحنى،
the famous scientist Francis Galton said,
قال العالم الشهير فرانسيس غالتون،
"It would have been deified by the Greeks if they had known it.
"لو عرفه اليونانييون، لعبدوه.
It is the supreme law of unreason."
إنه قانون اللامعقول الأبرز."
And there's no better way to materialize that supreme goddess than Galton's Board.
وليس هناك من طريقة لتجسيد تلك الإلهة الأرفع أفضل من لوح غالتون.
Inside this board are narrow tunnels
داخل هذا اللوح توجد أنفاق ضيقة
through which tiny balls will fall down randomly,
تسقط من خلالها الكرات الصغيرة بعشوائية،
going right or left, or left, etc.
تذهب يمنة أو يسرة، أو يسرة، إلخ.
All in complete randomness and chaos.
كل ذلك في عشوائية وفوضى تامة.
Let's see what happens when we look at all these random trajectories together.
دعونا نرى ما سيحدث عندما ننظر إلى كل هذه المسارات العشوائية معاً.
(Board shaking)
(إهتزاز اللوح)
This is a bit of a sport,
هذا أشبه بنشاط رياضي،
because we need to resolve some traffic jams in there.
لأننا بحاجة إلى فك بعض الاختناقات المرورية هناك.
Aha.
أها.
We think that randomness is going to play me a trick on stage.
نظن أن العشوائية ستخدعني على خشبة المسرح.
There it is.
ها هي ذي.
Our supreme goddess of unreason.
إلهة اللامعقول الأبرز خاصتنا.
the Gauss Curve,
منحنى غاوس،
trapped here inside this transparent box as Dream in "The Sandman" comics.
محاصرة هنا داخل هذا الصندوق الشفاف كشخصية دريم في كوميديا "ذ ساندمان".
For you I have shown it,
لقد أريتكم إياها،
but to my students I explain why it could not be any other curve.
لكن بالنسبة لطلابي فإني أفسِّر لهم لماذا لايمكن أن ينتج أي منحنى آخر.
And this is touching the mystery of that goddess,
وهذا يلمس لغز تلك الإلهة،
replacing a beautiful coincidence by a beautiful explanation.
عن طريق استبدال الصدفة الجميلة بالتفسير الجميل.
All of science is like this.
هكذا هي كل العلوم.
And beautiful mathematical explanations are not only for our pleasure.
كما أن التفسيرات الرياضية الجميلة ليست لمتعتنا فقط.
They also change our vision of the world.
فهي تغير رؤيتنا للعالم أيضاً.
For instance,
على سبيل المثال،
Einstein,
إينشتين،
Perrin,
بيرن،
Smoluchowski,
سملشويسكي،
they used the mathematical analysis of random trajectories
استخدموا التحليل الرياضي للمسارات العشوائية
and the Gauss Curve
ومنحنى غاوس
to explain and prove that our world is made of atoms.
لتفسير وإثبات أن عالمنا مخلوق من الذرات.
It was not the first time
لم تكن هي المرة الأولى
that mathematics was revolutionizing our view of the world.
التي تُحدث فيها الرياضيات ثورة في نظرتنا للعالم.
More than 2,000 years ago,
منذ أكثر من ألفي عام خلت،
at the time of the ancient Greeks,
في زمن اليونانيين القدامى،
it already occurred.
حدث ذلك بالفعل.
In those days,
في هذه الأيام،
only a small fraction of the world had been explored,
جزء صغير فقط من العالم قد تم اكتشافه،
and the Earth might have seemed infinite.
والأرض قد تبدو لانهائية.
But clever Eratosthenes,
ولكن إراتوستينس الذكي،
using mathematics,
باستخدام الرياضيات،
was able to measure the Earth with an amazing accuracy of two percent.
كان قادراً على قياس الأرض بدقة متناهية تعادل 2%.
Here's another example.
هنا مثال آخر،
In 1673, Jean Richer noticed
في عام 1673 لاحظ جون غيشي
that a pendulum swings slightly slower in Cayenne than in Paris.
أن البندول يتأرجح بشكل أبطأ قليلاً في مدينة كايين مقارنة بباريس.
From this observation alone, and clever mathematics,
من خلال هذه الملاحظة وحدها، والرياضيات الذكية،
Newton rightly deduced
استنتج نيوتن بشكل صحيح
that the Earth is a wee bit flattened at the poles,
أن الأرض مسطحة بعض الشيء عند الأقطاب،
like 0.3 percent --
بما مقداره 0.3 %--
so tiny that you wouldn't even notice it on the real view of the Earth.
متناهية الصغر لدرجة أنك لن تلاحظ ذلك عند الرؤية الحقيقية للأرض.
These stories show that mathematics
هذه القصص تظهر أن الرياضيات
is able to make us go out of our intuition
قادرة على أن تخرجنا من حدسنا
measure the Earth which seems infinite,
فنقيس الأرض الشيء الذي يبدو لانهائياً،
see atoms which are invisible
ونرى الذرات غير المرئية
or detect an imperceptible variation of shape.
أو نكشف عن انحراف ضئيل في الشكل.
And if there is just one thing that you should take home from this talk,
وإن كان هناك شيء واحد فقط يجب أن تخرج به من هذه المحادثة،
it is this:
هو هذا:
mathematics allows us to go beyond the intuition
تسمح لنا الرياضيات بالذهاب أبعد من الحدس
and explore territories which do not fit within our grasp.
واكتشاف مناطق توجد خارج متناولنا.
Here's a modern example you will all relate to:
هنا مثال معاصر سيمت إليكم جميعاً بصلة:
searching the Internet.
البحث على الإنترنت.
The World Wide Web,
الشبكة العنكبوتية،
more than one billion web pages --
أكثر من مليار صفحة إليكترونية--
do you want to go through them all?
هل تودّ البحث فيهن جميعاً؟
Computing power helps,
القوة الحوسبية ستساعدك،
but it would be useless without the mathematical modeling
لكنها ستكون عديمة النفع من دون النمذجة الرياضية
to find the information hidden in the data.
لكي تجد المعلومات المخفية في البيانات.
Let's work out a baby problem.
هيا نحل مشكلة بسيطة.
Imagine that you're a detective working on a crime case,
تخيل أنك محقق يعمل على لغز جريمة،
and there are many people who have their version of the facts.
وهناك العديد من الناس لديهم نسختهم الخاصة للحقائق.
Who do you want to interview first?
من تود أن تقابل أولاً؟
Sensible answer:
الجواب المنطقي:
prime witnesses.
الشهود الرئيسييون.
You see,
أترون،
suppose that there is person number seven,
افترض وجود شخص رقم سبعة،
tells you a story,
يخبرك قصة،
but when you ask where he got if from,
ولكن عندما تسأله من أين أتى بها،
he points to person number three as a source.
فيشير إلى الشخص رقم ثلاثة كمصدر لها.
And maybe person number three, in turn,
أو ربما الشخص رقم ثلاثة، بالمقابل،
points at person number one as the primary source.
يشير إلى شخص رقم واحد كمصدر رئيسي.
Now number one is a prime witness,
الآن، رقم واحد هو شاهد أساسي،
so I definitely want to interview him -- priority.
لذلك بالتأكيد سأود إجراء مقابلة معه--الأولوية.
And from the graph
ومن الرسم البياني
we also see that person number four is a prime witness.
نرى أن الشخص رقم أربعة هو شاهد رئيسي أيضاً.
And maybe I even want to interview him first,
ولربما أود إجراء مقابلة معه أولاً،
because there are more people who refer to him.
لأن هناك العديد من الناس يشيرون إليه.
OK, that was easy,
حسناً، كان ذلك سهلاً،
but now what about if you have a big bunch of people who will testify?
ولكن الآن ماذا لو كان لديك مجموعة كبيرة من الناس سيدلون بشهادتهم؟
And this graph,
وهذا الرسم البياني،
I may think of it as all people who testify in a complicated crime case,
ربما أفكر فيه كحالة كل الناس الذين سيدلون بشهادتهم في لغز جريمة معقد،
but it may just as well be web pages pointing to each other,
لكنها أيضاً قد تكون صفحات إليكترونية تشير إلى بعضها البعض،
referring to each other for contents.
في إشارة لمحتويات بعضها البعض.
Which ones are the most authoritative?
أيها الأكثر موثوقية؟
Not so clear.
ليس الأمر واضحاً.
Enter PageRank,
ادخل موقع PageRank
one of the early cornerstones of Google.
أحد الأركان الأساسية الأولى لموقع Google.
This algorithm uses the laws of mathematical randomness
هذه الخوارزمية تستخدم قوانين العشوائية الرياضية
to determine automatically the most relevant web pages,
لتحدد تلقائياً الصفحات الإلكترونية الأكثر صلة،
in the same way as we used randomness in the Galton Board experiment.
بنفس الطريقة التي استخدمنا بها العشوائية في تجربة لوح غالتون.
So let's send into this graph
إذاً هيا نرسل في هذا المخطط
a bunch of tiny, digital marbles
مجموعة من البليات الصغيرة والرقمية
and let them go randomly through the graph.
ونتركها تنطلق بعشوائية خلال المخطط.
Each time they arrive at some site,
في كل مرة تصل فيها إلى موقع ما،
they will go out through some link chosen at random to the next one.
ستنتشر خلال رابط أختير بعشوائية للذي يليه.
And again, and again, and again.
ثم مرة أخرى وأخرى وأخرى.
And with small, growing piles,
مع أكوام صغيرة متزايدة،
we'll keep the record of how many times each site has been visited
سنستمر في حساب عدد المرات التي تم فيها زيارة كل موقع
by these digital marbles.
عن طريق هذه البليات الرقمية.
Here we go.
ها نحن ذا.
Randomness, randomness.
عشوائية، عشوائية.
And from time to time,
ومن وقت لآخر،
also let's make jumps completely randomly to increase the fun.
هيا نحدث بعض القفزات العشوائية تماماً لمزيد من المرح.
And look at this:
ثم ننظر إلى هذا:
from the chaos will emerge the solution.
من خلال الفوضى سيظهر الحل.
The highest piles correspond to those sites
أعلى أكوام تتوافق مع تلك المواقع
which somehow are better connected than the others,
والتي بطريقة ما أفضل ترابطاً من الأخرى،
more pointed at than the others.
أكثر بروزاً من غيرها.
And here we see clearly
وهنا نرى بوضوح
which are the web pages we want to first try.
أي الصفحات الإلكترونية نود تجربتها أولاً.
Once again,
مرة أخرى،
the solution emerges from the randomness.
الحل ينبع من العشوائية.
Of course, since that time,
بالتأكيد، منذ ذلك الوقت،
Google has come up with much more sophisticated algorithms,
توصلت Google إلى خوارزميات متطورة أكثر من ذلك بكثير،
but already this was beautiful.
ولكن بالفعل كانت تلك جميلة.
And still,
وما تزال،
just one problem in a million.
مشكلة واحدة فقط بين كل مليون.
With the advent of digital area,
مع مجيء المنطقة الرقمية،
more and more problems lend themselves to mathematical analysis,
تلائم المزيد والمزيد من المشاكل نفسها مع التحليل الرياضي،
making the job of mathematician a more and more useful one,
مما يجعل عمل الرياضيين أكثر فائدة،
to the extent that a few years ago,
إلى حد أنه قبل بضع سنوات،
it was ranked number one among hundreds of jobs
صنِّف في المرتبة الأولى بين المئات من فرص العمل
in a study about the best and worst jobs
في دراسة حول أفضل وأسوء الأعمال
published by the Wall Street Journal in 2009.
نشرت على صحيفة Wall Street في العام 2009.
Mathematician --
الرياضييون-
best job in the world.
أفضل عمل في العالم.
That's because of the applications:
ذلك بسبب التطبيقات:
communication theory,
نظرية التواصل،
information theory,
نظرية المعلومات،
game theory,
نظرية الألعاب،
compressed sensing,
الاستشعار المضغوط،
machine learning,
الذكاء الاصطناعي،
graph analysis,
تحليل الرسم البياني،
harmonic analysis.
التحليل التوافقي.
And why not stochastic processes,
ولما لا العمليات العشوائية،
linear programming,
البرمجة الخطية،
or fluid simulation?
أو محاكاة السوائل؟
Each of these fields have monster industrial applications.
أي من هذه المجالات لديها تطبيقات صناعية ضخمة.
And through them,
ومن خلالها،
there is big money in mathematics.
تدرّ الرياضيات أموالاً وفيرة.
And let me concede
واسمحوا لي أن أعترف
that when it comes to making money from the math,
عندما يتعلق الأمر بتحقيق مكسب من الرياضيات،
the Americans are by a long shot the world champions,
يعتبر الأمريكييون ولدرجة بعيدة أبطال العالم،
with clever, emblematic billionaires and amazing, giant companies,
بقيادة مليونيرات أذكياء ورمزيين وشركات مدهشة وعملاقة،
all resting, ultimately, on good algorithm.
يستند جميعهم في نهاية المطاف على خوارزمية جيدة.
Now with all this beauty, usefulness and wealth,
الآن مع كل هذا الجمال والفائدة والثروة،
mathematics does look more sexy.
تبدو الرياضيات أكثر إثارة.
But don't you think
لكن لا تظنوا
that the life a mathematical researcher is an easy one.
أن حياة الباحث الرياضي حياة سهلة.
It is filled with perplexity,
إنها مشبعة بالحيرة،
frustration,
والإحباط،
a desperate fight for understanding.
وقتال مستميت من أجل الفهم.
Let me evoke for you
دعوني أريكم
one of the most striking days in my mathematician's life.
أحد الأيام الأبرز في حياتي الرياضية.
Or should I say,
أو كما ينبغي لي أن أقول،
one of the most striking nights.
واحدة من الليالي الأبرز.
At that time,
في ذلك الوقت،
I was staying at the Institute for Advanced Studies in Princeton --
كنت أقيم في معهد الدراسات المتقدمة في برينستون--
for many years, the home of Albert Einstein
لسنين عدة، كان منزل إينشتين
and arguably the most holy place for mathematical research in the world.
وكما يزعم، المكان الأقدس للبحث الرياضي في العالم.
And that night I was working and working on an elusive proof,
وفي تلك الليلة كنت أعمل وأعمل على دليل صعب المنال،
which was incomplete.
والذي كان ناقصاً.
It was all about understanding
كان الأمر يدور حول فهم
the paradoxical stability property of plasmas,
خاصية الاستقرار المتناقض للبلازما،
which are a crowd of electrons.
وهي عبارة عن حشد من الإلكترونات.
In the perfect world of plasma,
في عالم البلازما المثالي،
there are no collisions
ليس هناك من اصطدامات
and no friction to provide the stability like we are used to.
وليس هناك من احتكاك لتوفير الإٍستقرار كما تعودنا.
But still,
ولكن ما يزال،
if you slightly perturb a plasma equilibrium,
إذا ما أربكت قليلاً استقرار البلازما،
you will find that the resulting electric field
ستجد أن المجال الكهربائي الناتج
spontaneously vanishes,
سيختفي من تلقاء نفسه،
or damps out,
أو يصاب بالرطوبة،
as if by some mysterious friction force.
كنتيجة لقوة احتكاك غامضة.
This paradoxical effect,
هذا التأثير المتناقض،
called the Landau damping,
يسمى مضاءلة لاندو.
is one of the most important in plasma physics,
هي واحدة من الأكثر أهمية في فيزياء البلازما،
and it was discovered through mathematical ideas.
وقد تم اكتشافها من خلال الأفكار الرياضية.
But still,
وإلى الآن،
a full mathematical understanding of this phenomenon was missing.
يعتبر الفهم الرياضي الكامل لهذه الظاهرة مفقوداً.
And together with my former student and main collaborator Clément Mouhot,
وبصحبة طالبي السابق والمتعاون الرئيسي كليمينت موهوت،
in Paris at the time,
في مدينة باريس حينها،
we had been working for months and months on such a proof.
ظللنا نعمل لشهور وشهور على هكذا دليل.
Actually,
في الواقع،
I had already announced by mistake that we could solve it.
أعلنت مسبقاً عن طريق الخطأ أننا حللناها.
But the truth is,
ولكن الحقيقة هي،
the proof was just not working.
أن ذلك الدليل لم يكن يعمل.
In spite of more than 100 pages of complicated, mathematical arguments,
على الرغم من مايزيد عن مئة ورقة من الحجج الرياضية المعقدة،
and a bunch discoveries,
ومجموعة من الإكتشافات،
and huge calculation,
وحسابات ضخمة،
it was not working.
لم تكن تعمل.
And that night in Princeton,
وفي تلك الليلة في برينستون،
a certain gap in the chain of arguments was driving me crazy.
كانت هناك فجوة معينة في سلسلة الحجج تثير حفيظتي.
I was putting in there all my energy and experience and tricks,
وضعت فيها كل طاقتي وخبرتي وخدعي،
and still nothing was working.
وأيضاً لا شيء يعمل.
1 a.m., 2 a.m., 3 a.m.,
الواحدة صباحاً ثم الثانية صباحاً ثم الثالثة صباحاً
not working.
لا شيء يعمل.
Around 4 a.m., I go to bed in low spirits.
وحوالي الرابعة صباحاً خلدت إلى النوم بروح متعبة.
Then a few hours later,
ثم بعدها بساعات قليلة،
waking up and go,
استيقظت وأنا أقول،
"Ah, it's time to get the kids to school --"
"آه، حان وقت أخذ الأطفال إلى المدارس--"
What is this?
ما هذا؟
There was this voice in my head, I swear.
أقسم أني كنت أسمع هذا الصوت في رأسي.
"Take the second term to the other side,
"خذ الحَدّ الثاني إلى الجانب الآخر،
Fourier transform and invert in L2."
قم بإجراء تحويل فوريه ثم اعكس عند L2"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Damn it,
اللعنة،
that was the start of the solution!
كانت تلك بداية الحل!
You see,
أترون،
I thought I had taken some rest,
أعتقد أني أخذت قسطاً من الراحة،
but really my brain had continued to work on it.
ولكن فعلياً استمر عقلي في العمل عليها.
In those moments,
في هذه اللحظات،
you don't think of your career or your colleagues,
لا تفكر في مهنتك أو زملائك،
it's just a complete battle between the problem and you.
إن هي إلا معركة كاملة بين المشكلة وبينك.
That being said,
هذا يعني،
it does not harm when you do get a promotion in reward for your hard work.
لا يضرّ عندما تحصل على ترقية مقابل عملك الشاق.
And after we completed our huge analysis of the Landau damping,
وبعد أن أنهينا تحليلنا الضخم لمضاءلة لاندو،
I was lucky enough
كنت محظوظاً بما يكفي
to get the most coveted Fields Medal
لأحصل على ميدالية فيلدز الأكثر طلباً
from the hands of the President of India,
من يد رئيس الهند،
in Hyderabad on 19 August, 2010 --
في مدينة حيدر أباد في 19 أغسطس 2010--
an honor that mathematicians never dare to dream,
وهو شرف لا يجرؤ الرياضييون على الحلم به،
a day that I will remember until I live.
يوم سأظل أذكره ما حييت.
What do you think,
ماذا تظنون،
on such an occasion?
في مناسبة مناسبة؟
Pride, yes?
الفخر، ،نعم؟
And gratitude to the many collaborators who made this possible.
والامتنان للمتعاونين الذين جعلوا هذا الأمر ممكناً.
And because it was a collective adventure,
ولأنها كانت رحلة مشتركة،
you need to share it, not just with your collaborators.
تحتاج أن تشاركها ليس فقط مع الذين تعاونوا معك.
I believe that everybody can appreciate the thrill of mathematical research,
أؤمن أن أي أحد يمكنه أن يقدر تشويق البحوث الرياضية،
and share the passionate stories of humans and ideas behind it.
ويشارك القصص المشوقة للبشر والأفكار وراء ذلك.
And I've been working with my staff at Institut Henri Poincaré,
ولقد ظللت أعمل مع فريقي في معهد هينري بوانكاريه،
together with partners and artists of mathematical communication worldwide,
جنباً إلى جنب مع الشركاء والفنانين في الاتصال الرياضي حول العالم،
so that we can found our own, very special museum of mathematics there.
حتى نستطيع بناء متحف الرياضيات المميز خاصتنا هناك.
So in a few years,
لذلك خلال سنين قليلة،
when you come to Paris,
عندما تأتون إلى باريس،
after tasting the great, crispy baguette and macaroon,
بعد تذوق الرغيف الفرنسي الكبير والهش وحلوى بياض البيض ماكارون،
please come and visit us at Institut Henri Poincaré,
رجاء تعالوا لزيارتنا في معهد هينري بوانكاريه،
and share the mathematical dream with us.
وشاركونا الحلم الرياضي.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)